all right welcome to active infan stream
10.2 it's February 23rd
2025 I hope we will stay online long
enough through the storm for what should
be a very interesting time so thank you
everyone for watching keep an eye out in
the live chat let's jump right into it
all right I'm going to start with a
GitHub push and an obsidian push so this
is all going to be going to the repo
active inference Institute SL
cognitive starting the
[Music]
stream GitHub
push
then over in
obsidian I'm going to do an OB obsidian
push so that will be going live to
the publish. obsidian DMD slactive
inference
page and we
will select the changed
documents and the new 138 documents
okay obsidian push going live GitHub
push double check it and then let's Jump
Right
In All right we are in it so this is
going to be a little bit wild there's
parts that are in various and multiple
states of
functionality it's just too fun not to
share though so wanted to update and
follow up on the plain text series and
continue to give people some checkpoints
and
Milestones and open the space for their
suggestions and contributions to some
very exciting new ways of learning and
applying active inference so let's start
with the agenda here's the the windows
that I have for reference I'm going to
put the GitHub window away maybe we'll
push later in the Stream there's going
to be three main windows up there's
going to be a browser where we have the
GitHub repo and the obsidian publish
format and some other stuff's going to
pop up in here later we have the
obsidian window here where we can do uh
Force directed
graphs and this was used also in the
previous PL Tech stream then we have
cursor 45
running along mostly using agent mode
with the Claude 3.5
Sonet
so the stream being the second in the
plain text series is going to look at
learning paths application guides and
more things the stream will focus on
advancing our understanding and
application of active inference and
cognitive modeling Concepts through
learning paths detailed application
guides initially for RX andf for. JL
Julia package and a generic things repo
with a test Suite that's almost too
comprehensive giving some challenges
still and other
resources we're on YouTube and
elsewhere the information is all linked
here and we'll see where code viz comes
into play all right we begin with the
GitHub push let's check in first with
the generic things okay the
visualizations that were only minutes
prior working just fine of course failed
to work but that's totally fine they
really are all in there and uh I'm going
to pop over
to the
things generic
thing this is seeking and several dozens
of prompts and scribbles along the way
towards a foundational implementation of
activ inference principles through a
generic quote thing that can engage in
message passing belief updating free
energy minimization in a potentially
interactive nested Federated
situation um it's a little bit of a
balance with the markdown files because
there's things that look good on the uh
markdown display of GitHub and less so
in obsidian and vice versa so let's look
over to it in
[Music]
obsidian the core idea here as has been
suggested and
and indexed towards by many over the
years is what is that generic active
inference thing what is it that we can
have that's such a flexible schema that
it'll allow us to deal in continuous and
discreet time continuous discrete State
spaces single agent interacting with the
environment multiple agents dissolving
agent environment all these different
kinds of ideas that are out there and
then where PL text is heading and this
repo and this Vector of collaborative
research is with a lot of the pieces of
information be they
analytically former formal uh
Expressions be they in even probably
evocative other plain text
representations and eventually
multimedia then when we say Implement
variational free energy minimization or
Implement expected free energy
minimization we can know that it's going
to use retrieval augmented generation
rag like approaches to use that
information in the repo to structure the
discussion so a lot of the focus over
the last several days let's resume
it's um just in terms of what cursor is
doing in the background um I'm having it
run the test
Suite again and
again
while let's see what these ones will not
look
like um having it run the test Suite in
the background in agent mode where it's
going to make changes re run the test
suite and and so I found that this kind
of agent semi-autonomous semi-supervised
test Suite operation is super effective
um but here's a few of the key elements
so I wanted to have the capacity to have
the generic thing of course interact
with other things this could be Alice
and Bob just having that classic
conversation that Quantum classic
conversation or it could be agent
environment or it could be multi-agent
situations um here's the concurrency
diagram in terms of the message passing
now this was a very interesting topic
that we'll probably return to when we
get to RX infer later is to what extent
do we want to schedule the logistics of
message passing because as it is with
all this General active inference thing
research it's like what is the least
opinionated schema nothing what is the
most opinionated schema well it might be
super effective for where it's
effectively opinionated but it's not
going to have degrees of freedom so
which are the degrees of freedom that we
really want to engage with when for
example reactive message passing in RX
and fur which we're going to return to
makes some of this message
Logistics
possibly not necessary for the scheme
but again if it's a scheme that's
maximally unin ated it's just an empty
repo uh I focused on the message passing
functionality where starting with a
three things that were connected in a
linear
chain with a lot of
test
functionality
within the message um passing
architecture hello Jeff and
Monir um here is the
logistics of the action perception Loop
in active inference again one could
remain even more unopinionated on the
ordering of the action perception Loop
The Ordering of the udal loop and that's
the degree of Freedom that RX and fur
allows us to relax but here I wanted a
langu Independence scheme and just a
draft hopefully one where we may
actually come to realize that we do want
to make the schema already pre-adapted
to reactive message passing however if
we relax the logistics here so that the
reactive message passing can
proceed with the least opinionation then
that schema wouldn't be able to be
implemented outside of a react message
passing scheme because it'd be like well
where are the logistics and even within
a reactive message passing scheme we
still do need to have certain kinds of
event-based injections in order to get
the reactivity going so we have um
environment sensory internal and action
States external internal sense and
action being the blanket States
environment passes observations to
sensory which passes a belief updating
message okay here's the test Suite being
emitted so now this is what the
autonomous test Suite Improvement looks
like in cursor it pops out the test
Suite it is passing many of the
tests but some of them are still
failing and it makes a HTML
website that has a lot of useful
information
a massive fractal test Suite in fact and
then just continuing to say all right
fix it methodically agentically
professionally comprehensively continue
to run the test suite and go on and do
what you can to fix it and so on those
kinds of encouraging fractal prompts
so that for each of these core
functional elements of the generic thing
concept the core which we'll look at
free energy processes the inference
process Markov blanket depiction the
message passing which could be just the
standard uh kind of message delivery Pub
sub type or it could be more Federated
setup being needed in a visualization
script here then we have the test Suite
in the tests folder
which
gives these kinds of outputs so it's
going to continue debugging while we
look through
um uh from the internal States expected
free energy G across the pi list of
possible policies is calculated then
action is selected from the policy
posterior and then that executed
selection
uh of action the one hot action gets
passed back to the
environment so there are other
topologies and other ways to schedule
the logistics of this message passing
but again to the extent that we're less
opinionated about some of this stuff we
actually have like less and less of a
schema so without just having a piece of
blank paper or an empty repo empty mind
in front of us and say well this is
generic active inference how do we put
something into that
void and more
information as with much of procedurally
and probabilistically generated code it
has all kinds of quirks and features so
it isn't High reliability code per se
but it's awesome for what it is and it's
a starting point for line by line manual
investigation and curation and also for
further contemporary and F future
Advanced code repair
strategies um so
let's let it continue doing the test
Suite it's not giving the visualizations
it makes several dozen visualizations I
hope that we can get there by the end of
the stream somehow someway with several
a dozen I know that there's like a kind
of see it's a believe it element and
certainly the visualizations
provide really
important visual calibration and gut
checks and accessibility for these
processes that are happening um so we'll
check back in we'll make sure that the
um
autonomous test
Suite it'll stop after 25 agent tool
uses I don't think that's needs to be
that case but it is the case uh in this
version 45 with this current agent but
just so we remember
ensure that if and where possible we'll
we'll let it continue what it's doing
now but then it'll eventually say okay
that's all I could do right
now that visualizations are made
and
prioritized and fully logged with
full file name to a terminal okay so we
will uh return to the generic thing that
that's why starting to debug the generic
thing was first on the
agenda all right now to learning
paths so this
is
in okay just output
another test
report this is in
docks guides learning
paths okay so in the prior plain text
10.1 stream we were having a ton of fun
let's look at it in both GitHub I mean
we have three ways of looking at this we
have
the cursor
local so this is the code editor version
then looking also locally
is
Obsidian and then emulating that file
structure of the repo is the GitHub but
that won't be updated until the the push
is made but we can we can make that push
just for
fun let's see if there was any
visualizations made okay okay okay thing
generic thing visualization let's just
look at where it get
so thing generic thing visualizations
okay here we go just to sort of confirm
that the visualizations are happening in
the debugging so here we
go this is
the
action repertoire with summary
as well as precisions on actions and
some igen value Spectra on
that this is the action
repertoire these are belief States and
uncertainty these are output as part of
the test Suite so that's why these have
each time the test Suite is run some of
the um time stamping differs other
outputs are just without time stamp so
they're overwritten here's belief
updating
not sure how accurately it's
implementing basian
updating at least though the skeleton
and the architecture is
there free energy
histories here's the free energy
landscape from a parameter sweep
part of the free energy minimization
test looks like it's the same across
tests here's the
hierarchy some funky stuff happening
with the
labeling but a parent has child one and
child two and then a
grandchild here are the
uh sensor to processor so that's
from sensory to internal and then from
internal to
action patterns of input and
output here's the triadic internal and
blanket States for the
thing this is a two thing message
Network
processor see now it's adding more files
as this next round of the test Suite
continues to
occur more belief
State distributions correlation heat
Maps summary
statistics igen values on
matrices some very
interesting possibilities and hello
Ender
for spectral analysis on these random
matrices
uh temporal
Evolution this is a little bit of a kind
of sudo
mandron asking it for full details give
the full details the whole repertoire of
the sensory the internal and the action
States and those can be
described as a Through Time process as a
uh in time
process temporal analysis
looking at
sensor processor and actuator these
three
rows and the igen
value
Evolution test belief updating okay
another basian free energy landscape
this is a nice looking free energy
landscape
and roughly Concord with what we would
hope to see which is on this
manifold where the internal States like
-2 and -2 for internal external states
where they track each other they have a
lower free energy and to the extent that
they're off
that
manifold the free energy is
higher and a nice tetrahedral double
zigzag me message passing Network okay
so we're going to let the autonomous d
debugging proceed while we look
at the learning
paths these learning paths are
for
people and for non-
people so the way this worked is again
pop back however many minutes to before
where we saw from GitHub that the
visualizations were output we had all
these different topics across the
knowledge base which were more like idea
topics just to kind of remind on this in
the knowledge base there are these
folders so augmented reality and a
spatial
web and when you are in
obsidian the node that you're in
sometimes it's a little hard to find in
a big Network so here's spatial web and
then the what it's linked
to are topologically connected and we
can drag it around and see what comes
along for the ride so there's like that
spatial web and then connected to active
inference um so these are topics and
these these these are like fractal Wiki
Pages they could be line by line
versioned and annotated and calibrated
um as context windows in llms increase
and as the efficacy of putting very
large knowledge corpuses into finite
context Windows also improves relevance
realization improves there's really no
downside to adding more including a
plurality of perspectives on formalisms
on qualitative points these are all good
and exciting things so in the knowled
Bas folder I've added a few dozens of
more topics since last uh
stream so some of these are let's see
they look like they're okay it just
sometimes it takes a little bit old
Linux
laptop doing what it
can connecting with a lot of Bucky
Fuller stuff which those going through
the back catalogs will know has long
been a possible promise
exciting connection with synergetics
intensity and active inference um but
these are the knowledge based files
here's the
mathematics folder so calculus this
could be just one very very long several
hundred
page textbook it could be many textbooks
it could be calculus one or it could be
calculus adding more adjectives and so
on um category Theory same thing complex
system sys um and also it can get really
specific like
desparation which is a Criterion for
determining conditional Independence
relationships in basian networks so
going around and learning through each
of these topics is like exploring and
super
fun and yes needing to be verified and
checked and always possible to add
but it's like exploring in a lightly
synthetic intelligently peer-reviewed
Network um in the cognitive folder the
approach that I took was to make a file
called cognitive
phenomena and in obsidian you can choose
first off what you want the highlight
color to be so in the appearance you can
have accent color and it can be any
color you like so I like
red um the files that are linked and
exist are bright red and then there's
the dimmed ones which don't exist but a
single click will make that file and
just drop it into where uh the the top
level of the repo so the approach I took
with a cognitive folder was to several
times iteratively prompt okay let's
continue with the test Suite No we we
default stop the agent after 25 tool
calls please ask the agent to continue
manually please
continue to run and fix and improve the
test
Suite
okay um so several times iteratively
agentically methodically
comprehensively with adding a little bit
of Spice from the sideline throwing in
fly balls from left field and all that
added in different topics to this
cognitive phenomena index file and then
said now comprehensively
make the files that don't yet exist and
so just SP so this can be iteratively
done kind of like a two-stroke meta
engine where build out the
repo uh index add more cognitive
phenomena and it can there's no end to
how how much specific detail could
tesselate down and then the other stroke
of the engine is for the articles that
don't yet exist make them and for the
extent articles improve their dense
obsidian style linking and improve their
Technical and analytical and
applicability and accessibility and so
on one note I'll just footnote this is
all in English language but there's no
reason why it couldn't be on mass
translated and snapshotted um so that
was the cognitive
folder um citations this one is
empty really exciting collaborations
with the Gen 25 team and others so I
look forward to including people and do
and documents in in into this as well
but for now there's no people and
there's no papers um then over the last
uh little bit I also added in a lot of
Entomology and idology which is B
studies related topics and
micology which is ant studies so then
later on as may very well happen when we
say something
like make a generic thing
specialized for applying
to collective intelligence in
ants that is very well primed and
structured for the llm to be able to
make that adjacency and
bridge between what we already have
about
ants and what we already have about
generic things so this is in the um
there's also some fun topics like
mathematical entomology which I don't
really even know if I've heard of it
done specifically that way but it sounds
like it'd be a really exciting class or
topic kind of
connecting population biology Evolution
ecology development spatial
modeling cognitive science and behavior
experimental
design applications like for integrated
Pest Management and Biore Regional
stewardship and all these other things
and then it's like here are five current
research applications for mathematical
entomology people can have different
perspectives on where or how they would
value these research applications or how
close they are from the uh bench to the
bedside or whatever the ento equivalent
is but it's like something that can be
added to um and then also knowledge base
can include specific things like here
where we've done a lot of discussion on
the bio firm and this is like a
documentation fractal about the biofirm
addressing the kinds of topics and
questions that anyone exploring the
biofirm whether they be inner developer
membrane Communicator or
external somehow relevant to to learn
across this it's like how is active
inference applied in the
biofirm well here's an interactive
article on that and and this is all
available online like here's what it
looks like
online here's how the biofirm is doing
multiscale nested ecological active
inference and applying the free energy
principle and then lines can be
corrected or improved or added um but
again to get from a first pass to here
so rapidly is so fun okay so that's the
knowledge base now back to the learning
paths this was a new piece over the last
few days/ weeks so here
um still debugging away go get it
cursor learning paths again over the
years so many discussions well what's
the best entry point or and it was sort
of like the truth is a pathless land
like Krishna mury angle you know what is
the
one entry point and sort of a
recognition that there isn't just one
there's not just one entry point to
anything and so now the interactivity of
these tools is actually helping shorten
the active inference cycle and time udal
Loop timing to an absurd level for live
custom generative educational material
generation which could be done one shot
like you could just go to your favorite
llm generative AI chat interface and
say I like X please develop me a
curriculum for learning active inference
so that's something that didn't exist 5
years ago or 10 years ago earlier on in
learning active inference but that's
something where anyone with access to
those chat interfaces can get that one
shot but this is opening up with the
plain text repo the possibility for
having these
co-constructed and legible and credible
of different kinds learning paths and
one person asked in the Discord so the
learning path I forget which way they
even asked like does it go from active
inference to the area or or from the
area like well paths go both ways so how
about
octave okay I'm just I think it just
dropped for a second okay
okay it should be back but let me know
if anything in the chat if anything
weird
happens too many weird things are
happening to even say but I think you
all know what I mean by that so this
active inference economics
intersection can be used to take someone
from a more generic active inference
place or to to the domain or it can be
run in the other way I'm going to just
drop the bit rate on the stream a little
bit right on so um let's this is what it
looks like in the local
obsidian so here we
are and
this connects here's the active
inference economic learning
path let's go over to where it is in so
now we're going to look at
that I'm going to contrl a contrl k and
let's use the grock 2 model
comprehensively vastly add relevant
sections and Ensure
linking Style with
exent
files okay so here it is running
through adding
information to these sections we'll see
if it adds any new sections as
well okay ooh didn't like those parts
I I think that in the coming versions of
cursor they're going to be improving
this um and simplifying their kind of
fractal product offering in a way uh
unifying the chat and the composer or so
I heard from Gary um but we we we can
add this it's just that I have it
already running in the in the composer
with the debugging which maybe we can
just sort of we kind of get the picture
on the generic thing we get it that we
can write Mega fractal modu mod test
Suites and we can use that to do this
autonomous driven development on
different topics and we'll return to it
later in the Stream so I'm going to
start a new chat with the economics
learning path cons
comprehensively develop this more we
want to use this for a convening that
leads to a three
quarter co-learning course between
an
economics
department
and the active inference
Institute so that
all backgrounds and
familiarities with eg math
biology
economics Etc are
included and have many contributions
Avenues so then it's going to be doing
this
modification in
cursor that'll be live represented in my
local
obsidian and then we can push to
GitHub for it to then and and do the
shift publish to have it also go live
here so then
the idea of these learning paths one
idea of them
is biological learning path like this
URL or something very much like this URL
is like a stable URL and it can continue
to be developed out so instead of where
we would be just a couple months ago
okay I'm kind of curious about this I
really like to do um pottery and
embroidery and drawing and this is my
favorite you know just like where do you
start with active inference well oh well
here's the 2022 textbook and here's a
textbook group that's awesome that's
that's really hopefully exciting that
that's not every single Last Mile let
alone every last thto meter now there
can be a there could be active inference
micology learning path so that's from
somebody who's studying the
generalized active inference topic that
can take them out to the mological last
miles and from somebody who is working
on ants in the field take them
in towards this is just one way of
studying
it um okay here's it just laid it out
and we'll say
yes make all these additions
to the economic learning
hello reconfigurability trainer yeah
anyone if you have like a suggestion for
uh another learning path or a fun thing
to
try basically we're in the the middle of
act two of this stream where we're going
to look at the learning paths develop
the learning paths a little bit uh then
act three is going to go over to RX and
fur and explore some parad documentation
some fanfic documentation that I made
and then uh part four will be wherever
the live chat goes okay so here is the
modifications that cursor is making to
this economics
course so again just this is kind of a a
micro comment but when we use the
control K mode it deleted large sections
and then here it even recognizes through
the iterative process I noticed some
examples were deleted I'm going to add
them back
in okay so that's
happening so now
this has been expanded into that
multi-order course Concepts
okay so that's an example of improving a
learning path it could be
fractal unrolled into any level of depth
it could be we have 15 minutes and it's
a ninth grade classroom in this language
and here's what they're most excited
about or it could be it's a whole Lab
and there are five PhD students who are
ready to spend 5 years on this topic
okay m has made a
suggestion this is going to
be active inference
observation learning
pathmd so when wrote human judgment and
active
inference
especially the observer effect okay I'm
not sure if you meant this to be a a
learning path but I read it
so oh
okay and then followed up with this is
just a suggestion to see what active
inference agent self-perception about
its own belief
model okay let's turn this
into please comprehensively continue to
develop these ideas into a learning path
it's in the folder with all the other
learning paths so it knows a little bit
and about the structure and the template
and all of that um as a two-way street
beep beep for those
interested in such topics like as
described and
observation the art of
observation the magic and
possibility of
observation and active inference
parentheses
agents and Link obsidian Style
accurately but anyone can clone the
repo pull the active inference Institute
cognitive
repo get it going
locally navigate over to this folder
make a new file we'll do a micology
learning path
2 okay but here we're on the observation
learning path so it's like kind of like
phenomenology kind of like
ethology this learning path explores the
profound relationship between
observation human judgment and active
inference it examines how the AC of
observation itself shapes our
understanding and beliefs while
connecting these insights to the
mathematical framework of active
inference the path integrates
perspectives from cognitive science
philosophy of mind and computational
Neuroscience to build a comprehensive
understanding of how agents both human
and artificial perceive learn from and
influence their environment through
observation let's look over at it in the
obsidian setting so here's the
observation learning
path okay here it is Little Red
Dot here's what comes along for the ride
when we forc drag it
so let's
see foundations of observation
phenomenological approaches and
scientific interesting inner and outer
observation from the Blanket's
perspective oh
wait active inference Basics free energy
principle predictive processing Core
Concepts observer effect Quantum
measurement Theory social Observer
effects active inference and
self-perception belief updating and
interoception the Art of observation
mindfulness and attention Advanced
observation techniques oh brother
pattern recognition detailed perception
contextual awareness Advanced topics
computational models applications and
implications projects and
exercises
resources essential reading the
mathematics of Mind active inference and
agency by Carl friston I don't know if
that's a real paper but it's like we're
at the point where it's like does it
matter because we could generate what
would that
be okay would you like to add specific
content expand the
resources yes
vastly expand the sections related to
exercises there
should be so many access
ible
tangible
everyday experiences that will relate to
people's direct sensory and cognitive
experiences it should be a vast list and
one with many exciting starting places
for inner outer and social exploration
okay meanwhile let's just get the
micology
one write a
comprehensive learning path document for
micology we are a team of enthusiastic
quote field researchers
we are interested
in collective intelligence parenthese
and also
via
okay we'll look at that in obsidian in a
second and also via nested active
inference interested
in the
nestmate or the colony
make the learning path now please thank
you okay new
chat all right so now while the micology
path is unfolding
let's look at the observation
one thank you manir for the suggestion
that was
awesome okay now we're looking back to
the
observation all right here are the
projects and exercises let's see if any
of these strike are immediate
fancy inner World exploration sensory
awareness exercises one body scanning
practice practice I know of one cat
that's very interested in that two
breath observation series three
emotional weather
tracking second section of inner World
exploration cognitive observation
exercises thought pattern recognition
memory and perception studies attention
Direction experiments wow
outer World
exploration part one environmental
observation projects nature observation
series Urban environment studies object
Deep dive series wow single object
extended study material property
investigation function form relationship
object lifestyle tracking kind of a nod
towards systems
engineering pattern recognition
exercises visual pattern
detection sound pattern
analysis time pattern studies social
World exploration interpersonal
observation projects non-verbal
communication study conversation pattern
analysis group dynamics observation
cultural pattern recognition ritual
routine studies media pattern analysis
and computational Analysis okay now we
return to M
mology yes make the learning path math
much longer and include
EG math
diagrams artistic experience
possibilities okay while that's
improving a micology path let me check
the live
chat okay reconfigurability wrote what
are use cases that this can apply
to what do you think looking forward to
your thoughts munir thank you again
Andrew still catching up from start at
2x speed but you're you're having the 1X
experience of the 2x speed the economic
and biological learning paths are very
illustrative examples what about social
science curious how more specific and
general impacts and outcomes yeah I mean
one answer of course is I would look
forward to you adding that file and the
GitHub
repo uh making that social sciences or
we can make a Dub here okay let's let's
[Music]
um
yes
add many ant related topics colon deep
lore art culture and
folkways amazing historical and accurate
Natural History ant
anecdotes then we'll look at it in
obsidian okay reconfigurability has the
topic of underwriting been explored I
know that you really like that so let's
do a learning path active inference
underwriting learning
pathmd this is a
comprehensive make this a
comprehensive learning path
to and from the concept of
underwriting give
special thought and attention to the
domain specific ontologies that
beginners and experts across the active
inference and
underwriting
domains may bring complexly to such an
intersection okay looks good for the
ants we'll come back
there bring complexity to such an
intersection please be vastly
comprehensive
about
ontology
narrative tools
etc for
underwriting structure
this
massively okay make this happen
agentically comma methodically okay now
while it's doing the underwriting
learning path let's return to our
micology
okay so it's
off now this sometimes happens it's off
by itself all by its Lonesome but here's
how you edit it in
obsidian double
brackets and then start
typing first it suggests it to be
um there we go it just took a little bit
now we linked it to mycology so now it's
a red link because we already have that
file
micology so now here here we are now
here's micology connected to Earth's
system
schema interesting okay so let's see
active inference micology learning
path the learning path integrates
micology the study of ants with active
inference and Collective intelligence
Frameworks it is designed for
researchers interested in understanding
multiscale cognitive processes in ant
colonies from Individual
ants to Colony level Behavior see this
is the Crux of the issue later models
and other knowledge niches will not fall
into such a trap it's all about what you
call the individual individual ants
presupposing it as nestmate but it's
like okay I'm somewhat um startled I'm
surprised from nestm
to Colony level behaviors of
ants incorporating mathematical
computational and artistic
perspectives so math computational Core
Concepts of
micology active inference and social
insects research methods field
laboratory Advanced multiscale the
individual level it's all good it's all
good nestmate level single nestmate
but now this learning path can be used
in generating other materials and it
influences and so even though it's an
onto linguistic perspective that I have
that haphazard usage of the term
individual to refer to the nestmate
which would be equally inappropriate if
it were halfhazard used to describe a
colony is what makes the colony's
Behavior seen as collective intelligence
implicitly supposing that the nestmate
is the
individual whereas of course the
individual quote nestmate or just an
estimate is as with all cognitive
systems its own composition okay
artistic Creative Dimensions
let's let's have the
um yes please vastly continue to add
relevant topics sections exercises train
ings
reconfigurability
to this underwriting document
underwriting learning path document okay
micology
art scientific illustration technical
drawing ant morphology Colony
architecture behavioral sequence
sketching wow this is very classic
environmental context
drawing but if you look back in obl and
Wilson and all that if not much much
earlier this is what was there and some
of those are still in use and now with
generative AI we could make it look like
it was a different species and so on so
kind of cool digital art creative
documentation photography and
videography wow that reminds
documentation three art science
integration installation art
public engagement wow diagram types to
master scientific diagrams SD
mathematical visualizations artistic
representations and then we'll just add
in
category
Theory extended practical
projects
awesome okay mathematical
appendix
readings in interesting here the
superorganism by hold doin Wilson now
this is like a situation where the title
of the book falls into the Trap well if
the colony is the super organism then
that must mean that the nestm is the
individual
organism and that is the concept that
has grasped the imaginations and
constrained of
many wildly interestingly
historically active inference by par
pulo frisan at all but it's like here's
where the line wise editing
matters par pulo friston
2022 MIT
press there is also a textbook group
about this
book at
the Active
inference it'll take a second to load
this at the Active inference
Institute tools and equipment
additional dynamical systems in Social
insect even the concept of calling the
study of ants and bees social insects is
like oh so then the nonsocial would be
the nestmate and then the nestmates are
hanging out and that's the composition
of the social so it is baked in so
deeply into to the language of what is
social and solitary insect what is
individual and collective
intelligence
wow and now we can look at it line by
line career
paths fun okay ooh next steps join the
local mological Society everywhere could
have one all right let's go to the
underwriting all right then this will be
the end of this second uh phase then
we'll look at RX Ander documentation
parad documentation fanfic and then we
will go to phase four of the stream with
just whatever else people have added in
the live chat so thank you
reconfigurability for this suggestion
and right
now intra stream
update so I'm going to push that to
GitHub then in
obsidian shift period I set that it's it
you can set your own um keyboard
shortcut
changed and new 33 new
publish so that means that the
underwriting what's
a mological community yeah
reconfigurability I don't know but
micology is the study of ants so the
mological societies would be like local
ant Enthusiast researcher learner
chapters okay but let's look at it so
now we've pushed it
to obsidian publish so let's just look
at how it looks in um
docks guides learning paths here's
underwriting and then now over here
here's underwriting so to put this link
in the chat reconfigurability
there you go all
right this learning path provides a
comprehensive guide to understanding the
intersection of active inference and
underwriting designed for practitioners
from both domains seeking to bridge
these fields some of who might be in the
live chat I don't know prerequisites and
this is where it could link again more
densely um I'm going to have it do this
in cursor comprehensively
link
obsidian style to
relevant file names for EG
prequisites and
everywhere
possible so prerequisites probability
Theory risk assessment basic machine
learning statistical modeling you know
again somebody could say well I want
there to be a
the in the phase space of math and
computer science all the quadrants can
be explored it could be no math no
computer science version could be math
but no computers index card style could
be computers and no math gen Z Style no
I'm just kidding it could be math and
computer science together um okay domain
the underwriting domain onology this is
where the domain experts can say okay
what else needs to be added here in
terms of the Core Concepts key
processes active domain ontology this
draws on the models training which is
probably also on earlier versions of the
otim funology but also
um the files okay now it has upgraded
all of these so now this is cool so it
It upgraded all of these into the
obsidian linked format so save that now
in obsidian I'm going to do shift period
changed here's where the underwriting
learning path was changed publish
it now
wow so cool Incredible offering by
obsidian their software and their SYNC
feature just it it happened live didn't
it so now we can look at it
in our local
setup here's now what gets dragged but
previously it was not connected to
anything but now all of these and then
these ones that are dimmed these ones
could be
added but now we oh probability Theory
oh here's what probability theory
is oh what's a sigma algebra oh well you
know that could be linked but back to
the
underwriting um key processes you know
each of these could be documented
and then fundamental concepts for active
inference like yeah what is variational
inference oh open that up in a new tab
oh it's a method for approximating
complex probability distributions
through optimization
okay okay intersection integration
bridging concept risk modeling
decision-making and learning
systems application areas automated
underwriting portfolio management claims
processing tools and Technologies
technical stack okay learning
progression level
one understanding basic concepts so
underwriting principles again this could
be it says the link underwriting
principles does not exist but now in
here in the
relevant location in knowledge
base add and link to and from here the
quote underwriting
[Music]
principles file make it accurate
comprehensive
applicable and
more
okay so understanding basic concepts of
underwriting active inference and risk
assessment tool familiarization
integration Advanced implementation we
could think oh what about multi-agent
modeling in this situation just add it
foundations of risk assessment now it's
getting in another level of
detail active inference fundamentals
practical
implementations okay life insurance
underwriting property insurance health
insurance oh
wow Advanced
topics system integration Hands-On risk
calculator policy pricer automated
underwriting system four to six weeks we
could do it in four to six hours
portfolio Optimizer that one's tough
three to four weeks sounds good
certification
path level one level two level
three industry integration internship
program Junior underwriter technical
specialist mentorship program continuous
learning resources okay now here's the
underwriting principles so
now I'll push it
in
obsidian here it is in the
new
guides Concepts underwriting
principles okay so it was pushed
now remember
earlier it said that page doesn't exist
and and it
didn't but now now it's going to
be see where it mentioned it
underwriting principles now it's in
purple so now here are the underwriting
principles utmost good faith insurable
interest Indemnity approximate cause and
risk pooling
wow ubera
fides but this could just
be
semi-manually or fully automated or
anywhere in between continue to unfold
oh risk assessment we don't have that
one now
comprehensively add and Link the quote
risk
assessment file this will be the last
part on this and then we'll move to RX
infer and then anything else that
people suggest
okay but here we go risk assessment it
doesn't
exist okay
now it's going to write
that uncertainty
assessment yeah okay risk assessment
written
now even though it's probably going to
continue to update
it we'll push on obsidian so current
state we click on that the link does not
exist
okay so here's the old version of the
underwriting learning path now here's
one one of the issues
[Music]
um again brought up a little earlier
okay new select it publish it published
done okay so here current version risk
assessment does not exist so it's like
we made it en cursor The Prompt was just
add and Link risk assessment now reload
the
page this is the the on
the I'll put this in the live chat now
risk
assessment here's a whole
article risk assessment is a systematic
process of evaluating potential risks
and their impact in underwriting and
insurance
contexts this foundational concept
Bridges traditional underwriting
principles with modern active inference
approaches to uncertainty quantification
and decision-making it totally does wow
so that
was fun thank you and that was a
structured and structuring educational
Journey as we explored a little bit
about learning and cognitive modeling
all right now last section here um for
the for the RX andur Learners and
practitioners and then section four
would you like any other
healthy Whimsical fun suggestions all
right so here's what happened
in the RX in first
section
okay all right um well RX
Ander
is a software package being developed by
our
colleagues and it
is updating and developing in very
exciting ways we're really happy that
we're partnered with them and on this
co-learning journey and recently they
have done a big update on their
documentation as part of the version 4.0
4.01 now release and what's really cool
about this documentation site other than
the fact that it has an llm integration
with Gemini so you can chat with it
there but also this whole documentation
is a plain text file repo plain text
repo in the RX
infer uh
repository
so this docs and this is a very
professional software codery way to do
this the these documents are a website
but also the source code for the
documentation not just the code is also
available in the repo so what I did is I
took their SRC so here's source for
SRC right here from I did it within the
last couple of days I think and so
here's those same files so I just
in RX Ander repo online I just
downloaded their whole documentation and
I dragged it in to
docks then we're about to go through
some super fun um we you know we'll see
what names work you know is it is it um
is it
Paradox because it's off to the side of
the other docs is it heterodox because
it's different than their documentation
is it fanfic because I'm just a fan and
learner and just looking to make some
fun documents that help apply and
understand RX and fur I don't know
but here we
are let us go to read me so this is the
read me of RX and fur so this is I I
with their
SRC okay back to
here we're in
implementations there's a guides
implementations the the you know all
these folder structures can can be
evolved this is all just kind of like in
box as we learn some emerging practices
for what's happening here um but like we
we will do more and different and better
so everyone is welcome to learn and
contribute and raise issues in GitHub
and do more so here it is is the docs
here is where I copied in the SRC so
they already had this open source repo
with documentation I brought it in then
over in
cursor as always just like reyin the
cursor repo just a double check this was
when I was doing this and prompted
something like here make an obsidian
linked read me just to help totally
understand RX and fur so here's their
summary and that summary exists in our
repo too but now here we
are with the obsidian linked Style
with all these different loopy belief
propagation we've been
there and then I kept several you know
some of these code examples especially
it's like let us test them make sure
that they work and so on but then and
then we'll look through these pages
right now because it was like um what's
a big Topic in um RX and fur what's a
big motivator well doing reactive
message
passing so here here's the reactive
programming data sources reactive layer
and then the inference layer Core
Concepts stream processing
patterns error
handling performance considerations
these are all plain
text these are mermaid mind
maps so update frequency we can just add
timing
and now timing is right
there and it's and then when we push to
GitHub it'll be updated because this is
just a markdown and then when it's
published to obsidian sync it'll just be
there as part of the diagram message
passing in RX infer so just each time I
was like huh what would that Wiki
article be or what what would that
knowledge node be um so let's just look
through them we have active inference
examples
okay and then follow along in red with
where okay so here we are active
inference
examples were linked out to of course
the big heavy active inference one over
here that's probably real active
inference yep and then a bunch of other
ones around here so these are um
especially if these can be uh validated
and verified that they really run as as
we expect them to with the app models
that would be awesome but these are just
oh what are active inference examples in
RX Ander now they have that in the
examples in their
documentation so if you now we're on
their website examples examples. RX
in.ml and then here's like the active
inference Mountain car so a good cursor
a good
llm if we said make a new and we'll just
let's just do this right now just to
test it RX
infer Mountain
car readme.md
okay new
chat here write
a
comprehensively professional read me
specifically copying and invoking and
building upon
RX infers treatment of the
Classic mountain car
setting use obsidian links
densely ensure that all
analytical and RX and fur
syntax threads are fully unpacked
because the the in the docs folder in
the examples that it has that full
Mountain
car it it has the mountain
car but now it's going to write an
obsidian style read me about the
mountain
car okay Advanced systems engineering so
this was just for systems engineering
guide book
like the llms are trained on systems
engineering documents just like they're
trained to on a variety of other
technical documents so here's different
stages of model design and architecture
and life cycle design from a systems
engineering perspective and then this is
the advanced systems engineering guide
book I
guess um
okay let's look at the mountain car
here's the RX infer Mountain car read
me okay that part
could some stuff again it renders really
well in GitHub but not in a local
obsidian so so you know but then that's
where we get the metad docs that's like
we like this kind of linking and that
kind if it's called this or if it has
this template we like that if it's like
that we like this okay so we could check
does this this looks pretty
similar does that actually bring in oh
probabilistic model okay and then it's
like we already have that page but if we
didn't we could say write that page
go back inference constraints free
energy components active inference
framework optimize the expected free
energy let's link active inference there
double
bracket
active
inference so now it's a red link because
we already have that
page policy selection oh what is policy
selection it's
like middle
click how do we think about policy
selection in active inference well we
use expected free energy what are the
expected free energy components well one
decompositions epistemic and pragmatic
value what variabl is used to apply that
what notation or what letters it
associated with sometimes with the E and
so okay and then here's the running like
this just
generated this obsidian Style
plus plus
plus from the veritical mountain car
example that the developers
provided um yes add many more sections
as relevant including an intro section
that sets up a wonderful story as to why
we're solving
it this
way okay back to the RX and fer dos so
compiler
pipeline pending experts and others
questions and comments but this is very
fascinating to look at how it digs into
the documentation and the code
itself and pulls out some topics that
even in the year plus of learning about
this package we haven't
necessarily gone too much into detail
but this could help a lot with automated
code production and Improvement and also
onboarding and and better understanding
of performance all these different
features so that's the compiler
pipeline code
Generation all
right accept it back to the mountain
car imagine standing at the bottom of a
steep valley with an underpowered car
your goal reach the summit the catch
your engine alone isn't strong enough to
climb directly this is the Classic
mountain car problem but today we're
going to solve it in a fundamentally
different way not through traditional
reinforcement or optimal control but
through the lens of active
inference why active inference and it's
like and then the show is on the
road
okay um execution engine of RX and
fur here's what it looks like over
in
GitHub that top section looks like that
in the obsidian program locally but it
looks like
this on GitHub which is
epic execution
engine message flow
architecture optimization flow m message
passing message
scheduling cool Factor
graphs key
topic so this is a display kind that
doesn't work in the GitHub but let's
look at it over here let's see if it
looks
fine okay this one has an error let's
see if it can fix it Factor
graphs we are are getting some diagram
and markdown
weirdness and failures to render
properly on GitHub please expand
improve
obsidian style link and ensure total
comprehensive representation of RX infer
technical
contents within properly
appearing diagrams and
Etc okay free
energy how is free energy playing a role
in RX and fur how is it
calculated that's what this article is
and then it's like well this is like
very
technical that's a good thing it serves
as a
concise linkable place and also it can
be entered into with learning paths
write me a learning path to get to free
energy in policy inference as planning
in RX infer for an active inference
agent and I'm coming from this
perspective how does free energy play a
role in message
passing here's perception belief
updating with variational free
energy and then action in with expected
free energy and where they come together
that's epic message passing in active
inference some of this could
be lowkey fabricated but having the RX
inferred docs themselves
there gives a scaffold and if it was
ambiguous enough to um need so much
interpretation that's a sign to improve
the underlying documents and to improve
the
Paradox as
well um more details this one I just
said write write a followup give more
details on how free energy plays a role
in message
passing okay here okay it made the
improvements to the factor graphs
article let's return to factor
graphs this part still looks like it's
an error let's see if it saved
it push it to
GitHub okay so unable to render R
display reload it
new version just happened now still
doesn't work but people kind of oh wow
that's so cool that's Factor graph
style um getting started how do you get
started in RX and
fur
well here's conceptual PR
Rex here's the installation this looks
good
basic
concepts your first model coin toss
that's what we did
too visualizing using
plots more advanced features working
with
constraints custom distributions this is
getting into some pretty Advanced
examples um message passing the concept
model macro this is the at model macro
Paradigm this is because this is kind of
the core interesting syntax that opens
up an incredible world of
semantics the at model macro
automatically converts model
specifications into Factor
graphs it uses this app
model Style syntactically
to develop these enormously performant
reactive message passing setups which
can be used for batch learning or for
streaming models can have constraints
applied in any which
way and uh enables reactivity to occur
with this kind of subscription based
approach as that we could explore more
about that add another comprehensive
RX infer documentation page fully linked
about a abstract syntax
trees it's kind of an Arcane topic but
it
matters model
specification here's how you specify a
generative model in RX and
fur here's fanfiction in interactive
documentation about how you do
that um RX and first stack these are
some visualizations that I don't even
know if they've existed before new ways
and not necessarily even accurate ones
but sometimes on the path towards
utility and
learning
of the model specification through the
app model macro here's the as
transformation that's the abstract
syntax tree we're about to look at that
page that is being written right
now yes add vast
comprehensive sections to a page with
analytical details
diagrams
connections okay so the app model is
specified syntax
Wise It's transformed using this
abstract syntax
tree from that as
transformation The Factor graph is
compiled rules for message
passing are
compiled optimization passes are
performed we could look in more detail
what are those
then with the message rules just in time
prescribed and the optimization passes
of some kind we could explore situations
where they are and aren't coming into
play then there's this
execution engine that actually runs on
those rails as constrained and
specified through message passing node
local message passing free energy
minimization and there's some memory
management
too okay what is a parses the code
extracts the variables identifies the
dependencies generates a graph
optimization eliminates dead codes
merges optimizations and optimizes
memory
now we'll accept the as article let's
jump over to this new as processing
article abstract syntax trees play a
crucial role in model specification
within ARX andur the app model macro
transforms Julia code into an as which
is then processed to generate Factor
graphs for probabilistic
inference a type system is based on type
Theory
principles here's type theoretic
treatment of as
processing here's how it connects to
Julia
type abstract distribution continuous or
discreet two examples of continuous
distributions normal gaussian and the
and the
gamma message passing on
a memory management in a
and here's how a variational inference
is done in our
for here's streaming
inference in our
actioner
okay
[Music]
um let's look at one quick code viz
okay meanwhile um that completes our
primary
agenda let's reload this
window um at this time if anyone has any
requests or
ideas write
it
and I will stick around for a few more
minutes otherwise I hope this has been
interesting
useful possibly
relevant
um let's so here um code viz is is doing
its own
indexing all right let's do
okay I'll just make one
um
okay thank you reconfigurability okay
munir has written one suggestion
I'm just going to show how that how I'm
doing that there's I I know more and
better and different and relevant for
you um okay just like wait a minute like
where is everything
okay this is going to
be active
inference okay and then um
we'll just call that um path for for a
second when wrote I have another topic
experience as a method by Carl popper
and the least action principle free
energy minimization theory of mind I'm
curious to see the output as a learning
path all
right we'll call this experience as a
method or the paparian learning path
active
inference experience
do we want to make this like Jimmy
Hendrick
style experience method
path develop this learning path with the
stated topics
comprehensively including some Jimmy
hendris like St
ings quote are you
experienced
okay check out code
viz okay still the code VI sometimes
takes a while I know that they're aware
of that let's just see if it gets there
by the end of the Stream
Okay add
comprehensively obsidian linking to
extent
files
and Carl
popper philosophy everywhere possible
active
inference
pragmatism learning
pathmd this is kind of fun here's just
doing
tab autocomplete style and you can
get do we want to complete that one I
don't know if it's the
time but we'll okay so let's let's do
the
paparian okay that's the experience
method
one here in the
pragmatism path right vastly and
comprehensively related to American
pragmatism and
operationalism okay let's look at the
areu experienced learning path
are you experienced a journey through
active inference and scientific method
knowledge speaks but wisdom listens
Jimmy Hendrick I may be wrong and you
may be right and by an effort we may get
nearer to the truth Carl
popper okay experience as method walking
through the Purple Haze of knowledge
Carl Popper's epistemological
Revolution practical
experiments problem tenative solution
error elimination new
problem yes add more
information on the history of American
pragmatism
then that we're going to CU up this next
one returning to the experience method
add a
lengthy section contrasting the
paperian
hendris
epistemology with the
hegelian synthetic
dialectic method and
cont
okay we'll return to that one after
that's let's do little pragmatism
metaphysical Club absolutely Cambridge
Beginnings Holmes Wright James parce
Emerson Classical period 1878 to 1920
Pierce theory of
science James the Golden Age 1920 to
1940 mid-century transitions logical
empiricism
contemporary
Renaissance
interesting foundations of thought
operationalism and scientific practice
Bridgeman indeed it really was that way
whoa Neo
operationalism cognitive operations I'm
sure cognitive security otim through the
pragmatic lens social
Dimension so
cool so cool okay
okay let's go back to the experience as
method see if see if that hegelian
contian element has a Jimmy Hendrick
song that that reflects
it okay philosophical Crossroads bold as
love critical as
truth are you
experienced have you ever been
experienced well I have Jimmy Hendrick
experience is not what happens to you
it's what you do with what happens to
you Carl popper
wow hegelian dialectic the Purple Haze
of
spirit Conan Foundation transcendental
structures paparian Revolution electric
experience synthesis and contrast the
wind cries
method Wind Cries
Mary integration without AC inference
All Along the
Watchtower contian categories predictive
models hegelian development hierarchical
learning preparing and testing error
correction the story of life is quicker
than the wink of an eye Jimmy
Hendrick the growth of knowledge
proceeds from old problems to new
problems Carl
popper remember like hendrix's Mastery
of the guitar and Popper's Pursuit Of
Truth understanding these principles
comes through practice experimentation
and bold exploration let your mind be
free to experience predict and learn
while maintaining critical
thinking
okay here we'll just do one final one
ensure that this active inference so I'm
going to type this out generate it
probably read it if it looks funny and
interesting then I'll read any final
comments in live chat and then that will
be the end ensure that this active
inference learning
path
weaves delightfully around the who's on
first famous
dialogue the topics of active inference
and fre energy
principle should
be
comprehensively and technically conveyed
amidst
a rarified soup
of baseball
lore Timeless
comedy
wonderful wonderful science and the
occasional appearance by the ghost of
John Nash what wonderful
dialogue
intergenerational family Dynamics and
deep pH okay that sounds good deep
philosophical questions of identity
agency and the nature of of
reality as
interpreted in
a question question 20's golden quote
golden
era of American culture in technical
terms that are accessible to a wide
audience
ensure detailed
baseball
lore
and active inference all
along the Every
Way new
chat make this
happen structure the learning path
itself as who's on first not just in
semantic
reference all
right code VI so you still gather 11
minutes in still frozen so what is this
code
base this is a large repo so I kind of
get
it vastly expand vastly expanding this
learning path ensure
technical math sections and topics and
diagrams and
[Music]
obsidian
linking and long long long conversation
conveying so much lore and and
information comma it really does Boggle
the
mindes
yeah cursor indexing works really
well code
viz not quite there for large databases
yet
okay thank you Jeff thank you Andrew
Monir yeah we'll see where this gets us
if it's like funny and interesting
possibly read it
then that'll be
it welcome to a unique okay active
inference learning path who's on first
introduction the perfect game of Mind
welcome to a unique EXP exploration of
active inference and the free energy
principle structured as the immortal
Who's on First comedy routine just as
abbid and Costello's routine plays with
language and expectations will use their
format to unpack the fascinating world
of how brains make
reality okay there we
are for for those who like a little
topological
side with their baseball
comedy all right
right okay I don't think I'm going to
read this whole thing but it's clearly
funny let's just see what happens act
one tell me about active inference okay
brains predictions technical interlude
first
base you're saying there's someone
called prediction on first who's on
first I'm asking you who's making the
predictions Deep dive second base
strategic
play historical baseball analogy
M just as Bill James revolutionized
baseball with saber metrics Carl frisan
transformed Neuroscience with a free
energy
principle that should be an obsidian
link okay whoa sensory input prediction
who free energy what action I don't know
it's like the UDA Loop but for comedy
but for the 19 1920s but for baseball
but for future
audiences Third Base action
selection The Outfield extended
Concepts okay little bit of little bit
of dialogue little bit of chatter little
bit of peanut
gallery practice
drills who's making predictions
predictive processing exercise what's
the free energy mathematical workshops I
don't know is on policy selection
here we go historical context the 1920s
Golden Era baseball statistics meets
brain
statistics that is super
cool add many more connections about
baseball statistics and brain
statistics
give PhD
dissertation level and length about how
statistical
parametric mapping
SPM for
sages even the future of
advanced
baseball
analytics SPM could be you know
posterior probability maps for where the
ball is pitched or hit okay baseball
statistics meet brain statistics Babe
Ruth's batting average as a probability
distribution Miller Huggin strategy as
policy selection and the 1927 Yankees as
a predictive processing
machine cultural
integration Advanced topics the perfect
game statistical
Bullpen notes for Learners okay W see it
just changed while we're in it
okay now here's the statistical SPM meet
saber
metrics hey Abbot these numbers are
making my head spin that's because
you're looking at them like box scores
you need to think about them like brain
Maps gum random field theory in baseball
and brains it it literally is that
way Advanced analytics the convergence
spatial normalization and player
normalization literally it is that
way temporal basis functions pitch
sequencing effects fatigue
modeling statistical
methods it's like I feel like people are
ready for SPM applied to baseball but
baseball applied to
SPM is Evergreen
okay I'll read this last comment and
then any other live chats and then it's
over remember just as abbid and cella's
routine seems confusing at first but has
a clear internal logic active inference
might initially appear complex but
follows coherent principles keep
practicing and soon you'll be running
the bases of cognitive science
like a
pro ending of number 0
10.2 push the
GitHub then in
obsidian push the new and the
updated done close
obsidian okay ending of
10.2 close
it thank you Claude
and so many ways we can continue from
there but that's where I'll call it for
tonight so I'm glad that the internet
held up mostly well enough to make this
happen looking forward to where people
take it all from here so till next time
peace for